Guide to the John Jay Iselin papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
John Jay Iselin papers,
1983-1995
Iselin, John Jay.
8 linear ft. (8 record storage cartons)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1587
9006537
Papers of John Jay Iselin, journalist, editor, professor of journalism, and president of both WNET/Channel 13 and the Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art.
Biographical Note
John Jay Iselin, descendent of the Supreme Court Justice John Jay, was born in Greenville, South Carolina in 1933. He left South Carolina to pursue his education at Harvard, where he received both his Bachelor's Degree. He received the prestigious Marshall Scholarship which funded his course of study at Cambridge, where he received his Master's Degree before returning to Harvard to pursue his PhD in government, which he received in 1964.
After graduation he worked as a journalist for publications including Newsweek before shifting his focus onto the production side of writing as an editor with Harper & Row in 1970. He only held his editorial position at Harper & Row for two years; in 1972 he took the helm of New York's public television station, WNET/Channel 13 and remained president of the station for 16 years. Under his leadership, WNET produced shows such as Great Performances, Nature and Newshour as well as a number of documentaries and miniseries.
Iselin left the station in 1988 when he was appointed the tenth president of the Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art. His presidency there was marked with great growth in the Cooper Union endowment and in particular a huge capital campaign that helped build and update the institutions facilities and lab spaces. He also oversaw the creation of new endowed professorships. After twelve years at the Cooper Union, Iselin left the university to take on the presidency of the Marconi International Fellowship Foundation at Columbia University which promotes work and scholarship in the field of telecommunications, merging his own background in both the academy and in broadcasting.
John Jay Iselin died in 2008 at the age of 74.
Scope and Content
The records, which primarily cover the period in which Iselin served as the President of the Cooper Union, contain topical files and correspondence related to his professional activities.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 2 series
Series I: General Files, 1984-1993
Series II: Reading File (Correspondence), 1984-1995
Subjects
Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art.; Herb Lubalin Study Center of Design and Typography.; Iselin, John Jay.; College presidents; Correspondence
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Office of the President, The Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art Gift 09/08/2011
- Series I: General Files, November, 1984-November, 1993
  The General Files contain information relating to Iselin's presidency of the Cooper Union, including files on his fundraising efforts on behalf of the institution and research files related to the history of the Cooper Union, as well as files related to capital projects at the Cooper Union and a Charles and Ray Eames film festival hosted by the college.
  - Campaign, November 1st, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Gift Securities Procedure, May/June, 1987 (Box 1)
  - CU-Garden, 1992/1993 (Box 1)
  - Fringe Patterns Exhibit, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Freedom of Information Clearinghouse, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Forms-Various (Box 1)
  - Financial Reports and Mailing Lists, 1983-1990 (Box 1)
  - Centennial Campaign Convocation, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Childesign, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Commencement Info, 1983-1990 (Box 1)
  - Community Programs, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Computer Information, 1985-1987 (Box 1)
  - Conciliation Tour May 4, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Christmas Gift List, 1990-1992 (Box 1)
  - Continuing Education Programs Sept/Dec, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Cookerly, Anne,1990 (Box 1)
  - Cooper Collection Background Info, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Cooper Pioneer (copies), 1993 (Box 1)
  - Cooper Union History/Info, 1983-1991 (Box 1)
  - Cooper Union-125 Years, Fall, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Cooper Union Overview, 1991 (Box 1)
  - CU History (Box 1)
  - Cooper Union Research Foundation, 1983-1991 (Box 1)
  - A Festival of Eames’ Films
    - Mailing List, 1985-1987 (Box 1)
    - “Great Performances” (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Program (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Budget (Box 1)
  - State Dormitory Authority Loan, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Demographic Services Grenzebach & Martstl, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Deferred Giving to CU, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Energy Forum May 6th, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Engineering-H.S. Summer research internship program, 1989-1991 (Box 1)
  - Engineering School Info/Memos, 1987-1994 (Box 1)
  - Plaque Commemorative Updated List (Box 1)
  - Lubalin Center
    - Portfolio, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1986-87 (Box 1)
    - Contribution/Ad Response, 1986 (Box 1)
- Series II: Reading Files (Correspondence) 1988-1995
  Iselin's Correspondence Files, which he calls reading files, span his years at Cooper Union years and relate his work as the president of that institution.
  - December, 1989 (Box 2)
  - November, 1989 (Box 2)
  - October, 1989 (Box 2)
  - September, 1989 (Box 2)
  - August 1989 (Box 2)
  - July, 1989 (Box 2)
  - June, 1989 (Box 2)
  - May, 1989 (Box 2)
  - April, 1989 (Box 2)
  - March, 1989 (Box 2)
  - February, 1989 (Box 2)
  - January, 1989 (Box 2)
  - December, 1988 (Box 2)
  - November, 1988 (Box 2)
  - August 1988 (Box 2)
  - July, 1988 (Box 2)
  - June, 1988 (Box 2)
  - May, 1988 (Box 2)
  - April, 1988 (Box 2)
  - March, 1988 (Box 2)
  - February, 1988 (Box 2)
  - January, 1988 (Box 2)
  - December, 1990 (Box 3)
  - November, 1990, (2 Folders) (Box 3)
  - October, 1990 (Box 3)
  - September, 1990 (Box 3)
  - August 1990 (Box 3)
  - July, 1990 (Box 3)
  - June, 1990 (Box 3)
  - May, 1990 (Box 3)
  - April, 1990 (Box 3)
  - March, 1990 (Box 3)
  - February, 1990 (Box 3)
  - January, 1990 (Box 3)
  - January, 1991, (2 Folders) (Box 4)
  - February, 1991 (Box 4)
  - March, 1991 (Box 4)
  - April, 1991 (Box 4)
  - May, 1991 (Box 4)
  - June, 1991 (Box 4)
  - July, 1991 (Box 4)
  - August 1991 (Box 4)
  - September, 1991 (2 files) (Box 4)
  - October, 1991 (Box 4)
  - October, 1991 (Box 4)
  - November, 1991, (2 Folders) (Box 4)
  - December, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Deaths (Box 4)
  - January, 1992, (2 Folders) (Box 5)
  - February, 1992, (2 Folders) (Box 5)
  - March, 1992, (2 Folders) (Box 5)
  - April, 1992 (Box 5)
  - May, 1992, (2 Folders) (Box 5)
  - June, 1992 (Box 5)
  - July, 1992 (Box 5)
  - August 1992 (Box 5)
  - September, 1992, (2 Folders) (Box 5)
  - October, 1992, (2 Folders) (Box 5)
  - November, 1992, (2 Folders) (Box 5)
  - December, 1992 (Box 5)
  - January, 1993, (2 Folders) (Box 6)
  - February, 1993, (2 Folders) (Box 6)
  - March, 1993, (2 Folders) (Box 6)
  - April, 1993, (2 Folders) (Box 6)
  - May, 1993, (2 Folders) (Box 6)
  - June, 1993 (Box 6)
  - July, 1993 (Box 6)
  - August 1993 (Box 6)
  - September, 1993, (2 Folders) (Box 6)
  - October, 1993, (2 Folders) (Box 6)
  - November, 1993, (2 Folders) (Box 6)
  - December, 1993, (2 Folders) (Box 6)
  - General Correspondence, 1994 (4 Folders) (Box 7)
  - General Information, 1994 (Box 7)
  - Placement Advertisement, 1994 (Box 7)
  - Invoices, 1994 (Box 7)
  - January, 1994 (Box 7)
  - February, 1994, (2 Folders) (Box 7)
  - March, 1994, (2 Folders) (Box 7)
  - April, 1994, (2 Folders) (Box 7)
  - May, 1994, (2 Folders) (Box 7)
  - June, 1994 (Box 7)
  - July, 1994 (Box 7)
  - August 1994 (Box 7)
  - September, 1994, (2 Folders) (Box 7)
  - October, 1994, (2 Folders) (Box 7)
  - November, 1994, (2 Folders) (Box 8)
  - December, 1994, (2 Folders) (Box 8)
  - January, 1995, (2 Folders) (Box 8)
  - February, 1995, (2 Folders) (Box 8)
  - March, 1995, (2 Folders) (Box 8)
  - April, 1995 (Box 8)
  - May, 1995, (2 Folders) (Box 8)
  - June, 1995 (Box 8)
  - July, 1995